Tamzin: I think early interventions, are
really key because having worked in lots
of different young people fields, I think
the sooner the young people get help with
whether it be antisocial behavior, whether
it be mental health issues, or whether
it be help with kind of school issues.
Then the better outcomes they'll have.
Fran: By getting in there early,
it's sort of, again, it demystifies
mental health a little bit for them.
It helps them find coping mechanisms
that can be quite lasting, I think.
So.
If someone learns some techniques
that help with their anxiety when
they're 15, then there's a good
chance that those techniques will
still help them when they're 21.
Tamzin: I think the earlier the better,
because we have a lot of young people
coming through when they're 16 or 15,
and older, where they've not even kind
of been assessed for special educational
needs and they find that they're
frustrated because, obviously, parents
are frustrated or carers are frustrated,
the people are  frustrated because
they don't know what's wrong with them.
Fran: I think someone who's maybe has had
some form of mental health support when
they're 13, 14, they're more likely to ask
for it when they're 18, 19 if something
happens or then again, when they're 30, if
something happens that they need support
with, because I think, I think it can
be harder and harder to ask for help the
longer you go without ever receiving help.
Tamzin: Early diagnosis is key because
then obviously the outcomes are the
more support at school for them.
There'd be obviously more support
for the parents, more support for
them, obviously outside of school.
Everything would be a lot easier
in terms of like early intervention
for young people who are in
the criminal justice system.
Fran: We're not going to solve everything
for them in 12 sessions, but if they have
a good experience with me, and my support
or my organization at all, when they're,
when they're 13/14 then they might come
back to us or someone else when they
need it again when they're a bit older.
Tamzin: They've kind of been labeled
as "misbehaved" or "naughty" or
"attention seeking", when actually
they might have like ADHD or they
might have autism, or they might have
Asperger's and they've kind of gone
through life not knowing what it is.
Fran: If you're 14, you don't have a lot
of responsibilities and then you turn
18, 19, and you've got to move on and
start, you know, becoming an adult, then
if you haven't sort of already done some
work on those things that they can be,
they can really take over at that point
and prevent you from moving forward.
So I think the more we can do with
kids and young teenagers, the more
they're going to be able to progress.
Tamzin: Having worked at the youth
offending team, the young people,
the earlier they got help, the better
the outcomes it were for the young
people because I often found - we
often found - ourselves working with
10 year olds to like obviously 17
year olds and the 10 year olds, maybe
it was the first time offending,
obviously, 'cause it would be at 10.
And then if you get really good work
with them then you often find that
they won't come back into the system.
Whereas sometimes when they were a bit
older and they'd done a couple of offenses
then it'd be like a vicious cycle where
they'd be coming back in, coming back in.